Some CFOs are saying to data analytics
leaders, "Oh, sorry. I think in the past
few years you have pushed for me to
invest in data analytics. I always back
and say, okay, what's ROI?" Now, we have
even a higher level of pressure from all
the places.
So, we should have could have invested
more in data analytics two or three
years ago, earlier. Now, it's still not
too late, but still we should have been
could have been much more proactive.
>> Today on The Signal Room, I'm joined by
Gary Cao, long-time friend of mine and
executive leader who's been navigating
AI adoption from the inside of an
enterprise. Gary brings a perspective
shaped not by theory, but
accountability, aligning AI ambition
with operational realities,
managing risk while driving innovation,
and helping organizations move from
experimentation to enterprise scale.
As a chief data and analytics and AI
officer and serial founder of multiple
internal startups focused on data and
analytics across industries, Gary will
share his experience and lessons with a
focus on AI strategic road maps, and how
we can potentially integrate traditional
analytical AI with the emerging and
rapidly evolving generative AI
capabilities in the enterprise context.
Gary, welcome to The Signal Room.
>> Thank you, Chris. Happy to be here.
>> Well, I am happy to be having this kind
of a conversation and let a few folks in
on it. We've had some nice conversations
previously, and I always learn something
when we talk. So, thank you again for
for for joining me. I want to kind of
start with some things that are
really near and dear to your heart. I
know you've been talking about these
things a bit lately, and with all the
hype and the buzz going around,
I I I thought this is a really great
topic. So,
when you are talking to an organization
and they're saying they're on an AI
journey,
what does that usually mean in practice?
>> Generally, most companies when they say
they are in on an AI journey, they mean
they have
general very vague intention, and also
some type of
tool evaluation projects, use cases in
mind, but they don't have a holistic,
systematic way of designing a way
framework or road map for the next three
to five years. It's not just next month,
next quarter, even next year. It's
really I would say minimum one to three
years, if not three to five years.
>> Well, so
how do they go about really assessing
where they are then? I mean, if it's it
seems like it's not a orchestrated
strategy by what you're describing.
How would a a leader be assessing where
they fall on the AI maturity scale, do
you think?
>> Many companies are still, I would say,
in
maybe in a traditional journey of data
analytics, maybe in this
in a new phase of using generative AI,
but many many people's mind, those two
things are disjointed. They are not
properly, organically connected.
>> Right.
>> And when I talk to mid-size companies
CEOs and board members, I I ask them the
questions and say, "What do you want to
see in three to five years in terms of
the
future state of your company in terms of
the entire strategy, in terms of your
strategic priorities?"
>> Right.
>> From there, I want to see your strategic
plan and then from there translate that
into things that we can plan. Combining
four things together. One is technology,
which is the foundation. Without that,
you cannot do anything.
Second one is data. It's raw material.
The third thing is algorithm patterns
analytics. The fourth thing is the
business
adoption and execution of the
recommendation from analytics, pattern
detection and algorithm side. So, the
way we can see the real
or results of delivering the real value.
So those four things come together will
create a
virtual cycle to truly make this
capability development journey
sustainable and
truly delivering value that are expected
by the board as well as the CEO and the
owners and investors.
>> Right. Now, you you mentioned something
very, very briefly, but it's but it's
always a challenge.
Data
is always one of the biggest barriers
that I've run into, and I'm sure you've
seen this before, too. It's like people
have a different understanding of
the quality and completeness of their
data than than actually is reality,
which
kind of leads to another area I want to
touch on. I mean, we can pick up on the
on this
the data component of it because it's
it's a pretty significant lift, but
there's a gap usually between the
ambition and the execution. And I think
the elements that you described probably
fit into that gap in various ways, but I
mean, maybe talk a little bit about some
of the gaps that you see and and how do
you approach that?
>> That's great.
Um
I recently talked with a group of
people, practitioners in large companies
in technology, data analytics, and
digital transformation in uh
Cleveland area. We met at the Case
Western Reserve University
Weatherhead School of Management. We
talked about enterprise AI journey and
consistent with my professional kind of
framework based on past three years at
eight companies across industries,
I I identified four things to to kind of
like
as food food for thought. Number one is
business strategy. Without that, nothing
is really meaningful. Number two is
innovation and diversity of ideas,
analytics, and pattern detection, and
kind of like um algorithm-driven uh
recommendations, decision-making. Number
three is data management. And number
four is computing or technology or tools
infrastructure. So, all of those four
things, business strategy is the most
difficult topic for for discussion.
And innovation and diversity of ideas
and analytics
is less discussed. More discussed,
generally on top of people's mind, is
technology, tools, infrastructure, and
all those kind of things.
And then data management or data
quality, data lineage, data knowledge,
generally is below surface.
And also it's less, I would say,
undervalued, under-discussed.
So, all of those four things are
critical and are required to make this
journey less frustrating, more
successful, more productive. So, going
back, business strategy, analytics
culture, data management, and then
technology. So, those four things have
to be there. And technology is all
mostly visible and discussed. Data is
below the surface, sometimes out of
sight, out of mind. Analytics is less
discussed, still under-valued or maybe
under-appreciated. And business strategy
is generally
also difficult because people say,
"Okay, how do I connect the business
strategy with technology and problem and
use case and data management?" Because
data management just longer-term
requires much longer, let's say,
patience or deliberate effort.
>> Right. So, do you think that the there
there's a disparity between the
investment in the data foundation
versus what the ambition is? I think
that
I've seen it more often than not. It's
kind of there's a hidden cost that's
kind of tucked underneath the technology
contracts, and it's under-appreciated in
terms of the the level of effort when it
comes to getting the data fit for use.
What's your experience on that?
>> Yeah, data is it's not as tangible as
technology or tools. It's sometimes not
even visible.
And but that's the raw material. The
disparity here is that people try to
invest in the for the long term. They
are generally also very knowledgeable
about for example data, for example
technology. But the gap here is not
about investment in data management, but
rather
connecting data technology with business
problems.
And then focus on use cases and then
focus on short-term value creation.
>> Right.
>> And then have that connection traction.
That's the very interesting integration.
We have an integration of all those four
things together. That
Um many companies are very strong in
technology and sometimes also strong in
data. Business of course is
foundational. But the connection point
the the weakest spot
>> Mhm.
>> is the analytics part.
>> Right.
>> Which like a using technology and data
to
focus on the problem to solve it and
then deliver value with supporting and
servicing the business decision makers.
So that connection generally is not
easily um established or maintained or
>> Right.
>> supported.
>> Yeah, that's it's an interesting thing.
I mean I've I've been playing around
with my own models. I'm sure you have
too. But the quality of the the inputs,
the prompts, things like that,
um
they have everything to do with what
kind of an output you're going to
generate. And there's a lot of
variability as as well. Uh would maybe
if you don't mind, let's just talk a
little bit about how you see generative
AI kind of fitting in at an enterprise
level like it is part of an analytics
foundations. I don't know that uh we're
really clear on where the guardrails
are. But I know you spent some time on
that. I'd love to hear your thoughts.
>> It's confusing to many people.
Uh everybody says about AI, but in terms
of definition, people have different
definitions.
>> Right.
>> And in the common discussion or casual
dialogue, people mention AI casually and
there is something like AI
slop or AI wash.
>> Right.
>> In my mind, because I've been in this
data science machine learning space for
30 years for that for my entire career,
I believe AI's definition is pretty
broad. There are three layers. First
layer is the traditional data analytics
and machine learning,
predictive modeling, statistics,
mathematics, economics. So, that's
Of course, further including dashboard
and business intelligence.
>> Right.
>> And then the second layer that's kind
like
there, but people just don't necessarily
recognize they're there or see it is the
natural language processing, visual and
audio, and video image processing.
>> Right.
>> Uh, the third layer, which is more
visible in front of the use case users
as well as consumers, is generative AI,
large language model, the genetic
systems,
and uh
all the other hot and very dominant type
of topics right now. For example, chips,
for example, the large large language
model, for example, the visual video
creation, all those kind of things.
Those things coming together, there are
There is a clear line of evolution for
the past 20, 30, 40 years.
>> Right.
>> And if you don't people don't understand
the evolution, then they believe AI is
something
magically emerging in the past few
years,
>> Right.
>> then that's that's necessarily that's
missing the entire history.
>> Right.
>> So, if you look at the history, then you
will demystify AI and say, "Oh, it's
magic." No, it's not. It's algorithm,
it's statistics, it's economics, it's um
mathematics. So, if you look at that way
and um when people say, "Okay, I want
you." from the board of directors, from
CEOs, from CFOs, they say, "I want to
use I want to you use AI or generative
AI." What they really mean is that,
"Okay, I want to see results. I want to
see the what we're doing with the new
hot topics."
You That's not healthy in my mind. You
In reality, if you look at the entire uh
history and then make sure we start
um let's say, first crawl crawl before
we uh stand up and walk.
>> Right.
>> Walk before we start start running.
That's the capabilities Of course, I'm
not saying you have to do sequentially.
Sometimes you can
go back and forth, but then iteratively
uh without the right data foundation
uh without understanding the data
management side, anything that's kind of
like generative AI generated content for
example, customer service, for example,
uh meeting summary for example, new idea
generation. Those things are
helpful and useful, but they're not
going to fundamentally change the
decision process and culture and the
pro- uh let's say, workflow.
>> And I think that that gets to probably a
a point that maybe we don't talk about
enough for people to really wrap their
head around what this actually is about.
But, I know when we've talked, you've
talked about attention that kind of sits
between enterprise systems and
probabilistic AI models.
Uh there's
it's it's not magic. You know, I I I
figured that much out. I don't know that
I understand everything. But, talk a
little bit about what you know, what
that tension is between the enterprise
systems and probabilistic AI models.
>> I worked in health industry. I also
worked in financial service service
industry. I'm using the simple, let's
say,
different uh perspectives on functions.
For example, in financial service
banking industries, there's always
tension between marketing and risk
management. Marketing means that you
acquire new customers, you cross-sell to
customers with other products while they
have other have some other products.
And so, marketing is generally very
flexible
in terms of requirements. They don't
have any high level of accuracy in terms
of precision. So, once you have the
probabilistic decision-making process,
that's good enough.
But
in risk management, I think the
tolerance for lack of accuracy is much
lower. Of course, it's still
probabilistic. For example, you have a
model, you can say, "Okay, this group of
accounts have higher level higher
probability of
going to delinquent or something like
that." So, that's still probability.
But their requirements is higher and
this requires more compliance and more
calculation, more economic scientific
statistics analysis rather than rather
than tolerance of of the wider range of
ballpark number.
Um similarly in in healthcare, clinical
decision-making or diagnosis or
treatment, they have higher level of,
let's say, requirements for accuracy and
for higher level of compliance and
emotional value there. If you look at
administration and
let's say scheduling or let's say
logistics supply chain, those kind of
things are slightly I would say more
tolerant in terms of lack of accuracy or
precision. So, that's the healthy
tension between those different areas
for potentially applying
analytics. So, generative AI can
be very helpful for different use cases.
I have list of things that's really
valuable. For example, technical
assistance troubleshooting, right? For
example, content creation editing.
For example, personal professional
support. Those things are very
top use cases for generative AI. But if
you go back to say okay, I want to look
at the preventive, let's say um
equipment and machine machinery uh
maintenance. Those things will require a
little more statistical analysis and
then that at that moment it goes beyond
language models.
>> Right.
>> It goes to more mathematics um
statistics and then so it will requires
higher level of specialized expertise.
>> Right.
>> And a simple language model may not
handle that. Of course, of course, we
have a genetic systems that can
potentially blend in processes and
languages and also
let's say quantitative numbers. Uh but
we are not there yet. So we cannot
blindly trust, okay, language language
model can help us make better decisions
in just in traditional data analytics
can easily solve.
>> Right.
>> One great advance let's say
uh advancement here is that in the past
building a data science model may take a
few hours, a few days, or sometimes few
weeks.
>> Right.
>> Sometimes even months
depending on the complexity of the
product. But right now if you have the
right data and have high confidence in
data and also you have process work a
workflow defined. Right. That model
algorithm development can be as fast as
few seconds or few minutes.
So that enables a lot of data scientists
to be much more productive.
But does that reduce the workload and
attention to data quality, data
relevance, and data usefulness. All
those kind of things still have to be
there. Otherwise it's garbage in garbage
out.
>> Right.
>> And this also is it goes beyond
language. It's truly quantitative. The
other thing is that for our current data
management most of enterprises are still
using
relational databases, right? Data mart,
data warehouse, sometimes also they have
data lakehouse, data data lakes.
But they are tabular, maybe relational
data.
>> Right.
>> That's different from the more commonly
used data feed into generative models.
Generative model you you imagine that is
really more unstructured language,
visual, audio, those things. Or or log
files, right?
So the the the difference is there and
then uh generative AI greatly expanded
the
the capabilities or maybe the uh ability
for data scientists to use to expand or
speed up their uh workflow and to um
expand their scope of potential impact.
>> Right.
It occurs to me that you know what we're
talking about is an acceleration
uh of learning that typically would be
stretched out over a much longer period
of time. Just the pace that that's
generating new recommendations or
outputs just begs the question, do we
need a different kind of governance for
this generative AI approach to things
that's different than just what we
typically are doing for analytics?
>> I I think it's more complex and it's
more I would say there will be some
similarities and consistencies.
But there will also be some something
different, maybe going beyond the
traditional data governance. Data
governance has
has been I would say struggling for the
past few decades because it's uh high
cost and also it's it's very hard for
people to prioritize master data versus
the non
master data was kind of maybe maybe more
production data, right? Operational
data. So it's impossible to
to kind of like boil the ocean, right?
How do you balance the 80/20 rule in
terms of saying 80% of the
impact actually is deliverable created
with using the 20% of the volume of the
data." So, that could could potentially
be a great uh space generative AI can
help in terms of saying, "Okay, let's
look at the distribution and the focus
only on things that matter and also look
at the outliers and look at the things
that's out of the norm, then we can
correct that." So, the governance there
is probably useful, but the language
part of the the leakage part, many
people don't realize, "Okay, if we do
this, things already are out of the
door." It's not necessarily in front of
people's um
let's say computer.
That will require a discipline, it will
require, let's say, culture and
education and training and because
people have to realize we have we want
to minimize risks,
minimize the chance of making major
mistakes that
>> Right.
>> can cannot be reversed.
That has to be there first. And then the
many others kind of like smaller
potential problems, mistakes,
if we if we can recover from them,
yeah, we will just recover and gradually
we learn and then each turn each time we
will minimize chance of making the same
mistake in the future.
>> Right.
>> So, we don't have to worry too much
about it. But the big mistakes that you
want to avoid, that has to be really on
a high priority list for many um top
executives including the boards.
>> It it's just a whole different dynamic
to to be having the conversations, I
think, at an executive level
getting into the you know, the
differences between deterministic versus
you know, probabilistic thinking.
How should executives be thinking about
risk tolerance and cuz as you were just
talking about, there there's certain
certain areas that's just a
higher threshold that has to be met for
for something to be acceptable. I mean,
so how do they how do they should they
be thinking about that and
where's that margin
where you know that you've got a you've
got to make sure that you're hitting a
certain level of accuracy before
anyone's going to be comfortable that
you could trust it?
>> Yeah,
I think the business judgement is still
important, right? So,
I always go back to the fundamental
elements of the business, running a
business. So, first of all, you have you
have to have a customer.
And second of all, you have had have to
have some type of service and product
that can deliver value to the customer.
>> Yes.
>> And then then you have financial
performance, you have operations, you
have everything else.
From there, it's still right now human
judgement. So,
I would say
generally people most people are very
comfortable with mechanical
deterministic models. So, if 1 + 1 is 2,
okay, done.
But if you say 1 + 1 is
maybe 1.9, maybe 2.1, I don't understand
that. Why why do you say that?
So, in models, right, in probabilistic
data science or machine learning models,
it's all about patterns. It's all about
let's say judgement. So, I remember some
statistics
a statistician said, "All of the models
are wrong. Some models are useful."
Right.
I I always believe that, right? So, if
they all of them are wrong, then it
means okay, nothing is perfect
deterministic. So, it's really
probabilistic. So, it's a it's a mindset
mindset shift for leaders to say okay,
how do you balance the probabilistic
versus the deterministic?
In in reality, most business leaders
make
decisions based on judgement anyway.
For example, how do you know to invest
this many this much dollar amount into
this new product, going to this new
territory or market?
>> Right. all judgement.
>> Yes.
>> So, they should come to be
they are already comfortable
making
decisions based on limited information,
especially for you for example in
business, in military, in different
things. It's all the same
decision-making process.
>> Right.
>> So, as long as leaders remember business
foundational principles,
then just use that. And then again
generative AI is another
could be another tool, could be another
enabler, could it could be another For
example, people say kind of kind of like
a silicon, maybe a new digital species.
Okay, that might be too far in a
philosophical way, but from a business
perspective,
most enterprises are still in the early
stage of the journey for data analytics,
let alone generative AI.
And what I've heard is that some CFOs
are saying, "Oh,
uh saying to data data analytics
leaders, say, "Oh, sorry. I think in the
past few years you push for me to invest
in data analytics.
I I always push back and say, "Okay,
what's ROI?" Now we have even a higher
level of pressure from all the places.
So, we should have could have invested
more in data analytics two or three
years ago earlier. Now it's still not
too late, but still we should should
have been could have been much more
proactive. So, I think CFOs are also
some CFOs are all realizing that, "Okay,
until we push to the next level, then we
realize, "Okay, we are a little bit
behind." Even though they think ROI is
critical as
required, but ROI is not the only
uh decision criterion you have to use.
You also have to use judgment. You have
to use, let say,
intangible values. You have to use
culture factors. You have to use
strategic value of the different uh,
>> Right. I You mentioned something that I
I think is a
really important thing to to dial down
dial in on just a little bit. It's
really that we're talking about a
thought process that has to be
we have to instantiate it better and
make sure that we're not bypassing some
things because
when you're talking about patterns that
may exist in the data and facts that
exist in the data, uh, and it leads you
to predict things within some range of
acceptable percentage points, but
in reality, sometimes what's available
to us in history,
while true, is no longer the direction
we're going because we've learned
something. And so, I think that the
governance process has got to be a
little bit different than what we're
accustomed to. I think for that reason.
You know, you you can pick almost any
kind of scenario that you that you can
imagine, uh, but one of the best ones
I've heard was just this discri- this
disparity in salaries between men and
women historically in certain fields.
And that historical data would predict
certain things and tell you where it's
headed based on what it sees in the
history. That's where the judgment stuff
is so much more important and we have to
make sure that, you know, we're we're
designing our governance processes to
appropriately
pause and create space for those
judgment calls to happen so we don't get
ourselves into a spot that is, uh,
taking on more risk than we really ought
to be able to take on.
>> Yes. One other factor that I've seen
many companies, um,
may
not have spent enough time or investment
is the workforce upskilling. Right? So,
it's about mindset shift, it's about
ownership, it's about driving change
that's actually ultimately beneficial
for the company as well as for the
employees. So, that will require
sometimes some type of lifetime learn
lifelong learning.
>> Yes.
>> So, if you don't train them, they will
stay. If you train them, they will
leave. Okay, which one is better for
you?
>> Right.
>> Right. So, training and education and
upskilling
workforce
is great.
But, there are some other potential
concerns about, okay, if the AI is
really reducing the workforce, what why
would the workforce be welcoming the
adoption of AI?
>> Right.
>> So, that's another uh philosophical
discussions. It's about company culture,
it's about why companies exist.
>> Yeah, I think that's a it's a great
point and
I love that you're bringing up human
judgment and wrapping everything around
the support of human beings, which you
know, I I love that because it's it sure
is exciting to talk about the
technologies. I mean, it's it's it's
interesting and
I know people that think like we do
probably enjoy some of that technical
jargon and and investigating and
learning new things maybe more than
others. But, I think you're you're
making some really important
distinctions where this is not a
technology thing. This is really a whole
'nother level of support that we're
trying to put a wrap around the delivery
of good good health care. But, even
beyond the health care sector, same
thing is true. This is all really got to
support the lives of human beings and
make make their lives better in in ways
that we are
mitigating as much risk as we possibly
can. We're never going to bat a
thousand, but if we can get to 80 90 80
or 90% when we've never been able to hit
50%,
that's not perfection, but it's
certainly an improvement and I think
that's the the balance to be figured out
and the leadership has a has a really
important task to try to figure some of
these things out because the pressures
for cost and reduction and in
containment in health care, I don't
anticipate
really changing a whole lot. In fact,
there's an expectation that we're going
to be more efficient. And what does that
actually mean? It It really depends.
>> Maybe reducing the Maybe reducing the
waste. Maybe optimizing the resource
allocation.
>> Right.
>> Or maybe a better better alignment of
timing or geographical location. It's
kind of like a
>> I meant so I also see multiple
dimensions of disparities
>> Mhm.
>> in terms of adopting data analytics and
generative AI.
>> Yeah.
>> One is industry specific from, right?
Some industries are much more advanced.
For example, the digital native
companies
>> Yes.
>> versus manufacturing versus all
industries, right? So, they may be much
earlier in their
evolutionary stage. So, that's the
industry difference. The second one is
probably a geographical difference. So,
East Coast, West Coast versus South
versus Midwest. There may be
geographical differences because of
industry exposure and talent and other
factors. The third thing is within the
each company.
The difference or the disparity between
or the gaps between technical people
versus business people.
>> Right.
>> Business people, they think, "Okay,
don't tell me the details. I want to get
this thing done." And then But then the
business the technical people say,
"Okay, I know the technical aspect but I
have to I I don't know how to
effectively communicate with business
people."
And then so, many companies could
benefit in the in the future or right
now by identifying people and developing
people who can
fluently speak business language as well
as technology language.
And then data language and analytics
language, all those together.
>> Got it.
>> So, it's it's a it's a long-term
challenge or maybe long-term phenomenon,
but eventually it will get better. And
when we are in the journey, we're making
changes, the the progress can be slow
right now if we look at them. But if you
look back five three year five year
look back at today,
you will see we have traveled a long
distance. So, it's really about um
believing in the vision and believing in
the direction and then truly effort into
it.
>> Yeah, I I I think there's a there's an
interesting term that I've been thinking
about a lot lately in terms of what it
the kind of role that you're you're
describing that that you've been and I
I've spent a number of years in it, too.
But, the ability to do that translation
between the business and the technical
team
that can be that can't be overstated how
important that is. Um it's such a big
part of what you've done in your own
engagements, you know,
as as a
entrepreneur, but what also is
is a major player in enterprise systems.
That that's just such an important role.
And, you know, what it that doesn't
really matter what the title is. You
just need to have people that are, you
know, really good at understanding both
and bridging that communication uh gap
that often is existing because at some
point you're going to have to be held
accountable for what you're delivering
on. Which kind of brings me to one just
one thing on the business side I I'd
like to to have you weigh in on a little
bit
um before we pivot. I want you to put on
your
your special glasses and look in the
crystal ball and say and tell me what's
coming, but how should boards and
enterprises be evaluating
the potential ROI or lack thereof with
the with all the things that are coming
at them because, you know, you and I
have spent way too many hours
fishing through literally hundreds of
emails sometimes in a single day with
solutions providers covering a wide
range of things that may or may not be
viable, but even to do that assessment's
challenging. But, how would you say that
boards need to be thinking about that?
>> Yeah, at the end of the day, it's really
about judgment, about experience, about,
let's say, uh
of pros and cons and
benefits and costs. I would say that ROI
discussion can have um
two elements. One is value, the other
one is strategy or growth. I I actually
wrote an article in the past few months
and saying the board and CEOs, when they
look at AI investment, they should
balance the two approaches. One is
value, the other one is growth. So,
value is more very specific um
measurable metric in terms of ROI,
project-based, specific use case-based.
Growth is more strategic value in terms
of even hard-to-quantify
benefits. So, but you should not We
should not necessarily
discount or maybe
deprioritize the strategic value of
other AI investment. In my calculation
or potentially a scorecard design, there
are three components in this uh benefit
or
ROI. One is
direct impact on incremental revenue,
right? Or profitability. Second one is
cost avoidance or cost reduction. Those
are measurable numbers.
And sometimes you will say, "Oh, how
about number of hours saved?" That's
That's efficiency. That's another issue.
The third thing is benefits that are
hard to measure in dollar values even
quantity number numbers. For example,
customers' net promoter score
improvements.
So, those three things the decision
makers can assign given weights on those
three things and then come up with the
score. So, for example, one thing that
is has look low or no impact on revenue,
but has some light im- impact on time
saved or maybe cost reduction or cost
avoidance, right? But huge benefit in
quant- let's say qualifiable but not
quantifiable, let's say soft benefit.
Then
the decision maker should say, "Okay,
yeah, I know, but this this this is
something we should do. Even though it's
not short-term
>> ROI.
>> Yes.
>> Number-driven. Right.
>> So, CFO is has a lot of great input into
the discussion, but generally CEO is a
decision-maker or board board will make
a decision.
>> Right.
>> So, we should not necessarily let the
one metric just dominate the entire
discussion. So, it's it's really about
balancing. It's about making sound
decisions.
>> Right.
>> It's a different perspective, different
weights on different factors for the
decision-making.
>> Yeah, there's a
there's always a
difficult task sometimes.
If you're looking at things just from
how they contribute to a margin, whether
it's cost reduction or increased
revenue, that obviously is the top of
mind in in most conversations. But then
there's this other factor that probably
can be a whole lot more disruptive if we
don't get it right is when we're dealing
with um
some pretty difficult shortages um for
staffing, for nurses and clinicians,
particularly in the in in the general
medicine general internal medicine
space.
So, they they you know, they I love that
you kind of highlighted there's there's
more than one thing that you got to look
at. The numbers are important, of
course.
But those numbers are guaranteed to get
worse if you if you can't staff the the
clinicians that you need.
>> That's why
I I I I always believe that
everything has its life cycle, right?
So, one industry, one location, one
product,
uh one company, one person has its life
cycle. So,
>> Right.
>> there is a chance that the board of
directors or the CEO could
reinvent the company, a culture, a
business model to start a new life cycle
curve.
>> Right.
>> But that's not easy, right? So, if you
don't reinvent yourself, then it's
easier to just take the ride, and then
eventually the life cycle the It be
growth, and then stagnation, and then
decline. So, how do you bend the curve
from decline to be another new growth?
>> Right.
>> So, there will always be some type of
dynamics in terms of friction conflict
in terms of friction different tension.
So, it's always there. It's just a
matter of the company's life cycle and
also the the vision and the core value.
>> This has gone like super fast. I mean I
always enjoy our conversations.
If I can get you just kind of look out
little ways into the future over the
next like 3 to 5 years.
Two things.
What do you think
some of the most
important leadership skills and
capabilities are going to matter the
most?
And how do you see things shaking out in
terms of
the organizations that are going to
really come through this in in a really
really positive manner? What are the
characteristics of those companies and
the leadership that it's going to take
to do that?
>> I I think the most important trait for
leader or influencer is to solve
problems deliver value and also provide
service. Right? So, it's
if you are delivering valuable service
to the right customer
to the right stakeholder to the right
audience
>> Right.
>> you will be in a good position. To do
so, coming back to the potential traits
of the organization. It's the way to
deal with ambiguity versus specific
details. So, it's kind of trade-off
between specific ROI versus intangible
benefits. How do you measure that?
>> Right.
>> Another important trait for the
successful organization would be
workflow optimization architecture
design.
So, it's not about okay, you have a
rigid process. Okay, let it go
Keep, it's not broken, don't fix it. But
>> Right.
>> based on the market demand, based on the
customer need, how do you make this
workflow process steady, but also
continuously you evolve and improve.
That way we will
prevent this more
agile approach. So, when things change,
you can also change or be adaptive.
>> Right.
>> So, that be adapt be adaptive, that's
the
one very important trait for the future
companies.
>> I I really appreciate that. I I think
the concept of disruptive innovation has
been
around for as as long as time.
Um
>> Easy to say, very hard to do.
>> Right. But the challenges are going to
only get get a a little bit bigger now
because we're advancing at a pace that,
you know, none of us have ever
experienced in our lifetimes and it's
just staggering how fast the advances
are coming. Well
>> Yeah, I I I would say there are there
are two or three things I can leave with
with audience today is the number one is
that go back to the fundamental basics,
right? Don't forget about the core value
and principles and guardrails.
>> Right.
>> Um number two is balance of
probabilistic versus deterministic
approach. So, you need both. It's not
one or the other.
And the the third thing is
uh
for data analytics professionals, um how
do we
take advantage of the advancement of
technology
and uh uh of the environment.
Uh a lot of visibility, right? A lot of
awareness about data analytics.
>> Right.
>> How do we pivot from generative AI to to
the entire spectrum of data analytics?
And of course, including generative AI
and our generative stuff and all that.
>> Right.
>> Robotic process automation, right?
Digital process automation.
To focus on two aspects. One is data
management.
>> Mhm.
>> The other one is explainable
algorithm-based recommendations.
>> Yes.
>> Huge opportunities exist for data
management. How do we streamline this
entire data management process? It's
time-consuming, it's expensive, it's
also not not very accurate.
>> Right.
>> But then
so how do you streamline that using
let's say generative AI or using the
genetic process. The second one is
explainable algorithm-based
recommendations for business
decision-making. That will deliver
value as a last mile value delivery.
>> Awesome.
Well, Gary, I mean
as always,
really great conversation. I always
learn things when we talk. So, thank you
so much for for coming on the show and
and and you're sharing your your
experiences and your knowledge and
giving us a glimpse of what we should be
expecting over the next 3 to 5 years.
Sounds like we've got plenty of plenty
of work to do.
Um
>> Thanks very much, Chris. Happy to be
here and then I always support you in a
way that
I can. It's also benefiting the data
analytics professional as a community.
>> No, thank thank you so much. I really
appreciate you coming on the show.
I look forward to having you back to to
the audience.
Watch watch for the show notes. They'll
provide some information so you can
definitely reach out to Gary.
He's got some really great experience
and if if you have questions, you need
some help,
I know he can help you. So,
thanks again and that'll do it for this
episode of the Signal Room.
>> That's it for this episode of the Signal
Room. If today's conversation sparked
something in you, an idea, a challenge,
or a perspective worth amplifying, I'd
love to hear from you. Message me on
LinkedIn or visit signalroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode.
Until next time, stay tuned, stay
curious, and stay human.